Dr Rachael W Cheung, MBChB, MSc, MSc

Department of Psychology, Lancaster University, UK General Medical Council: registered clinician, non-practising r.w.cheung@lancaster.ac.uk https://cheungrw.github.io

Summary: I am a multi-disciplinary early career researcher with a sincere passion for conducting research about early experiences. My research investigates the environment surrounding language acquisition and how it affects the cognitive processes and behaviour of caregivers and their children. I also conduct research regarding more general learning mechanisms, and have a particular interest in comparing typical and atypical development and outcomes across a wide range of fields, including language development and psychiatry.

Education

2017 - current Leverhulme Trust Doctoral Scholar (Psychology PhD student)

Lancaster University

Thesis (provisional title): Characterising language learning and language outcomes in typical and atypical development

Supervisors: Professor Padraic Monaghan, Dr Calum Hartley (Department of Psychology, Lancaster University)

2014 - 2016 Developmental Neuroscience & Psychopathology MSc (Distinction)

University College London

Thesis: The effect of videogames on attention and resting state functional connectivity in adolescent males

Principle Investigator: Dr Michelle Hampson (Yale Magnetic Resonance Research Centre, Yale School of Medicine, Yale University)

2006 - 2012 Medicine MBChB

University of Manchester

2010 - 2011 Healthcare Ethics & Law MSc (Distinction)

University of Manchester (medical intercalation)

Thesis: Medical expert witnesses & clinical negligence: a time for change? Supervisor: Dr Catherine Stanton (School of Law, University of Manchester)

Prizes & Awards

2019 Faculty of Science and Technology Dean's Award for PhD Excellence

For outstanding performance in PhD

2017 - current Leverhulme Trust Doctoral Scholarship

Value per annum: maintenance stipend (£14,553), tuition fees (£4,195) and

research budget (approx. £5,000)

2011 Lord David Alliance Prize

For outstanding performance and best mark in Healthcare Ethics & Law MSc

Employment

2017 - 2018 Emergency Medicine – Locum Doctor (A&E Agency; SHO)

Salford Royal NHS Foundation Trust; Stockport NHS Foundation Trust

Jan - June 2017 Associate Medical Writer

Ashfield Healthcare Communications

Aug - Dec 2016 Core Trainee Psychiatry Doctor (CT1) - portfolio available

Pennine Care NHS Trust

2012 - 2014 Foundation Doctor (FY1, FY2) – portfolio available

Tameside & Glossop Acute Services NHS Foundation Trust

General Medicine & Endocrinology, General & Colorectal Surgery, Trauma & Orthopaedics, Paediatrics, General Practice (Community), Emergency

Medicine

Research Projects

2017 – current Leverhulme Trust Doctoral Scholar

Babylab / Department of Psychology, Lancaster University, UK

Longitudinal project: Predicting language outcomes in late talkers and

characterising how they learn (infant and child studies)

Cross-sectional projects: Gestures and multiple cues in word learning (infant

and adult studies)

With: Professor Padraic Monaghan, Dr Calum Hartley

Methods: Eye-tracking, behavioural, video-coding mother-infant interactions,

standardised testing, touch-screen behaviours

2015 - 2016 Clinical Research Fellow

Yale Child Study Centre / Yale Magnetic Resonance Research Centre,

Yale University, USA

Longitudinal project: The effect of electronic media on attention and fMRI in

children and adolescents

With: Dr Linda Mayes, Dr Todd Constable, Dr Dennis Sukhodolsky, Dr Mike

Crowley, Dr Dustin Scheinost, Chris Walsh, and Dr Michelle Hampson

Methods: Functional MRI (resting state functional connectivity), behavioural

Research Skills

Programming: R (proficient)

Analysis: General linear and mixed effect models, linear mixed effect models

Growth curve analysis of longitudinal data

Eye-tracking data analysis (HDF-conversion, fixation data; AOI based; growth

curve analysis)

Software: Analysis – SPSS

Eyetracking – Tobii Studio (Tobi X3-120) Task programming – E-Prime, PsychoPy3 Neuroimaging analysis – BioImage Suite Research – Qualtrics, NIH Toolbox

Video-coding – ELAN

Other: Microsoft Office, Adobe Photoshop

Publications

- **Cheung, R.W.**, Hartley, C., Monaghan, P. (accepted) The early cue catches the word: how gesture supports cross-situational word learning. *Proceedings of the 42nd Annual Conference of the Cognitive Science Society.*
- **Cheung, R.W.**, Hartley, C., Monaghan, P. (2019) Caregivers use gesture contingently to support infant word learning (under review)
- **Cheung, R.W.**, Hartley, C., Monaghan, P. (2019) Environmental effects on parental gesture and infant word learning. In A.K. Goel, C.M. Seifert, & C. Freksa (Eds.), *Proceedings of the 41st Annual Conference of the Cognitive Science Society*, 212-218.
- Humphreys, J., Obeney-Williams, J., **Cheung, R.W.**, Shah, N. (2016) Perinatal psychiatry: a new specialty or everyone's business? *BJPsych Advances* 22(6), 363-372.

Oral Presentations

- **Cheung, R.W.**, Hartley, C., Monaghan, P. (2019) Environmental effects on parental gesture and infant word learning. *Talk presented at CogSci 2019, Montreal, Canada.*
- **Cheung, R.W.**, Hartley, C., Monaghan, P. (2019) Environmental effects on parental gesture and infant word learning. *Talk presented at LCICD 2019 (Lancaster Conference on Infant and Early Child Development), Lancaster, UK.*
- **Cheung, R.W.**, Hartley, C., Monaghan, P. (2019) Word learning in typical and atypical development. *Talk presented at Department of Linguistics, University of Amsterdam, the Netherlands.*
- **Cheung, R.W**. (2017) A Junior Doctor's Perspective on Neuroscience and Psychiatry. *Talk presented with Professor Wendy Burn and Dr Gareth Cuttle, Royal College of Psychiatrists (Gatsby/Wellcome Neuroscience Implementation Project) at Lancashire Care NHS Trust, UK.*
- **Cheung, R.**, Constable, T., Mayes, L., Scheinost, D., Crowley, M., Hampson, M. (2016). From Mortal Kombat to Minecraft: Video games, Attention, and Resting State Functional Connectivity in Adolescent Males. *Talk presented at Yale School of Medicine, Yale University, USA*.

Posters

Cheung, R.W., Hartley, C., Dunn, K., Frost, R.L.A., Monaghan, P. (2019) Environmental effects on parent teaching and infant word learning. *Poster presented at WILD 2019 (Workshop on Infant*

Language Development), Potsdam, Germany.

- **Cheung, R.W.**, Hartley, C., Dunn, K., Frost, R.L.A., Monaghan, P. (2019) Preliminary results: environmental effects on parent teaching and infant word learning. *Poster presented at LCICD 2018 (Lancaster Conference on Infant and Early Child Development), Lancaster, UK.*
- **Cheung, R.W.**, Hartley, C., Monaghan, P. (2018) Environmental effects on parent teaching and infant word learning. Poster presented at the FST Postgraduate Conference, Lancaster, UK.
- **Cheung, R.**, Constable, T., Mayes, L., Scheinost, D., Crowley, M., Hampson, M. (2016). From Mortal Kombat to Minecraft: Video games, Attention, and Resting State Functional Connectivity in Adolescent Males. *Poster presented at Yale School of Medicine, Yale University, USA.*
- **Cheung W.**, Pramanik K., Warner R., Barton S., Trehan A. (2010) Converting Criticism to Change: Health Services Research in an Emergency Assessment Unit. Poster presented at 4th International Society of Acute Medicine Conference, Edinburgh, UK.

Public Engagement & Research Dissemination

2017 – current Babylab Lancaster Coffee Mornings (monthly free event for families)

Volunteer

2020 – current REF 2021 ICS (Faculty of Health and Medicine, Lancaster University)

Scientific Writer

I work directly with authors to identify and communicate key research impacts

for the Research Excellence Framework Impact Case Studies

2019 LCICD 2019 (Lancaster Conference: Infant & Early Child Development)

Organising committee member

2019 ESRC Festival of Science

Volunteer demonstrator for Babylab Lancaster

2019 Campus in the City 2019

Volunteer demonstrator

2018 The Communication Trust: Using Evidence on the Ground

Consultant with LuCiD and Professor Monaghan

I worked with speech and language therapists across the country, helping them select and evaluate interventions for early language skills (ages 0-5). I worked closely with a speech and language team that was piloting

interventions for language delay in an Opportunity Area in Derby

2016 - 2018 Royal College of Psychiatrists: Gatsby/Wellcome Trust Neuroscience

Project Implementation Group *RCPSYCH Appointed Member*

I served as a committee member for an implementation group designed to

integrate up-to-date neuroscientific research into psychiatry training

Teaching (portfolio available)

Summary: I am a self-driven, highly motivated, and enthusiastic teacher who has extensive experience in teaching both on-the-job and formally in tutorials, lectures, and seminars. I have always designed my own teaching materials (slides, hand-outs, group exercises) based upon curricula, and have used my initiative to ensure these sessions are engaging as well as informative. My additional roles as a representative have afforded me a good sense of pastoral care, and I have consistently positive student feedback for my teaching (available on request).

Awarded 2019 Associate Fellow of the Higher Education Academy (ref. PR169537)

Associate Teacher Programme, Lancaster University

2020 Department of Linguistics, Lancaster University, UK

2nd Year 228 Language Acquisition: Language Impairments, Guest Lecturer

2018 - current Lancaster Medical School, Lancaster University, UK

3rd Year Psychiatry tutorial leader (Mental Health Law, Personality Disorders,

Case and Poster presentations)

2017 - current Department of Psychology, Lancaster University, UK

2nd Year 205 Developmental Psychology Seminars, Associate Lecturer 1st Year 101 Developmental Psychology Seminars, Associate Lecturer

1st Year 101 Skills in Psychology, Associate Lecturer

2013 - 2018 Salford Royal NHS Foundation Trust, UK

Tameside and Glossop Acute Services NHS Foundation Trust, UK

3rd – 5th year medical students, University of Manchester

I delivered informal teaching throughout my clinical years to medical students on placement, and have had numerous students shadow me alongside doing

my day-to-day job

2012 - 2014 Tameside and Glossop Acute Services NHS Foundation Trust, UK

Junior doctor (FY1) tutorials: coroner's court, acute on-call conditions 5th Year (final) medical student tutorials, University of Manchester: OSCE

stations, history taking, clinical examinations, acute

presentations/management of disease, interpreting ABGs/test results

2009 - 2011 Medi-Quest Ethics & Law Tutoring, Salford Royal NHS Foundation Trust

UK

Group-based tutorials for secondary school students (14 – 18-years-old)

Representative Roles

current Postgraduate Research Student Representative (Lancaster

University)

2016 Junior Doctor Representative & Local Negotiating Committee

Representative (Pennine Care NHS Trust)

2012 - 2014 Foundation Trainee Representative (Tameside and Glossop Acute

Services NHS Foundation Trust)

Volunteer Work & Other Interests

2010 - 2011 Mediscope (Manchester Medical School Magazine) Editorial & Writing Team

2008 - 2012 Barnabus Manchester (homeless and red light district outreach) – weekly

volunteer

Languages: English (native); Cantonese (dim sum level); German (A1 level)

Music: Piano (grade 7), cello (grade 5), guitar (self taught)